Guide to the New York State College of Agriculture Dept of Botany records, [ca. 1882-1963]
New York State College of Agriculture Dept of Botany records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
New York State College of Agriculture Dept of Botany records, [ca. 1882-1963]
21-17-2491
New York State College of Agriculture. Dept. of Botany.
2 cubic ft.
Manuscripts, Photographs, Printed materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Photographs, prints, and lantern slides; memorabilia about Botany Dept. field trips and social activities, and department minutes.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Memorabilia, prints, scrapbooks, photographs and lantern slides of field trips, and meeting minutes related to the Dept. of Botany.
Photographs, including some of Barbara McClintock and Karl Wiegand; scrapbooks belonging to Professors Muenscher and Knudson; and diaries belonging to Professor Walter Muenscher.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State College of Agriculture.; Cornell University--Faculty.; McClintock, Barbara, 1902-1992.; Muenscher, Walter Conrad Leopold, 1891-1963.; Knudson, Lewis, 1884-1958.; Wiegand, Karl M.(Karl McKay), 1873-1942.
Subjects:
Botany -- Study and teaching.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Lantern slides.; Scrapbooks.; Diaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Department of Botany
  - Picnic Lists, c.1898-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Handwritten and signed attendance sheets for local field trips
  - Programs, Articles, and Cards, 1904-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes "History of Botany at Cornell(1868-1931): 25 Year Mark of Department" Also includes "Dichotomous Key to member of the Department of Botany," for others like this see volume 4
  - Copies of Historic Plant Catalogs (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Copies of plant catalogs from 1822 and 1831
  - Plant Physiology Seminar Sign-in Book, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Botany Department Minute Book, 1952-1961 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Also includes correspondence and articles
  - Department of Botany Memorial Volume I, 1907-1918 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    Humorous scrapbook - includes poems, stories, sketches, photographs, collages, and clippings from newspapers and magazines
  - Department of Botany Memorial Volume II, 1922-1936 (Box 1, Volume 4)
    Humorous scrapbook - includes poems, stories, plays, puzzles, and clippings from newspapers and magazines
  - Professor Lewis Knudson, 1952 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    Photo album and scrapbook containing letters and photos of the current lives of Prof. Knudson's former students
  - Botany and Plant Biology centennial materials, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photographs
    - Matted Photographs, c.1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Field Trips I: Candid people, c.1900-1940s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Field Trips II: Candid People and Landscapes, c.1900-1940s (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes a few color images, negatives, dated photos, and photos with lists of names of persons.
    - "Early Days of Botany," candid people, classroom, and Cornell Campus photos, c.1900-1940s (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes prints and negatives
    - Group Portraits: Cornell Faculty, Cytology, Ecology, and Officers of the Congress, 1910-1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Oversize
    - K.M. Wiegand, 1917-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Matted and loose photographs of field trips. Individuals in the photographs are named.
    - Students and Staff, c.1922-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Portraits and candid photos with individual's names written on the opposite side. Dated and undated
    - Botany Department Portraits, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Bound scrapbook
    - Department of Botany Group Portraits, 1938-1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Staff and Classrooms (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Prints and negatives
    - Professor Arthur Eames on his 80th Birthday, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Roll of 35mm negatives for Botany Department Portraits, 1935 (Box 1)
      See folder 15 for prints
  - Glass Plate Lantern Slides and Negatives (Box 2)
    - Plate Glass Lantern Slides, 1882-1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      3x4" plate glass sides of students, professors, seasonal field trips, classrooms, and the Cornell University campus
    - Plate Glass Lantern Slides, c.1929-1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Plate Glass Lantern Slides and Negatives (Box 2, Folder 3)
      3x4" plate glass sides of Tahiti and Fiji trip.
      Glass plate negatives(c.1885-1920):
      Negative Box 1 - classrooms, staff and the Cornell University campus.
      Negative Box 2 - Seasonal Field trips
      Some of the prints are among the photographs in Box 1 and in collection #14-29-2026
    - Plate Glass Negatives, c.1929-1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      4x5" plate glass negatives of trees
- Professor Walter C. Muenscher
  - Loose Photo album, 1918-1925 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes many portraits of the members of the Department of Botany during field trips.
  - Department of Botany - Dr. Walter C. Muenscher, c. 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Humorous puzzles and plays
  - Correspondence and Memos, 1954-1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Plaque Dedication, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Death Notices and Obituary, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Record, 1910-1920 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    Diary that includes hand written notes, news clippings and other paper ephemera
  - Record, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Volume 6)